A Guide to the Harvey Lee Price Papers, 1853, 1898, 1900, 1927-1949, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Harvey Lee Price Papers, 1853, 1898, 1900, 1927-1949, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1975-001
1.67 Cubic Feet; 5 boxes and 1 oversize folder
The Harvey Lee Price Papers contain handwritten notes and genealogies of various Montgomery County families which Price used to write his four volume series Outlines of Montgomery County Families. Also included are Price's subject files on the county and Virginia and his diplomas from VPI.
Price, Harvey Lee, 1874-1951
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Harvey Lee Price Papers were donated to Special Collections in four accumulations: two in the 1940s, one in 1975, and the final in 1984.
Biographical Note
Harvey Lee Price (1874-1951) was associated with Virginia Polytechnic Institute throughout his professional career, first as a student (B.S. 1898, M.S. 1900), followed by his extensive tenure as a faculty member in the Horticulture department (1900-1950). During those years, Price was an administrator from 1908 through 1920 and Dean of the School of Agriculture from 1920 through 1945. Price Hall, originally constructed in 1907 as Agricultural Hall, was renamed in his honor in 1949.
A descendant of early Montgomery County settlers, Harvey Lee Price had a strong avocational interest in genealogy and local history. His Outlines of Montgomery County Families has long been a valuable source for genealogists and historians. Hardback copies of the four volumes are available in the Rare Book Collection.
Scope and Content
The Harvey Lee Price Papers contain notes and outlines of various Montgomery County families which Price used to write his four volume series Outlines of Montgomery County Families. Materials consist of Price's own background research, notes, transcribed historical documents, and correspondence with numerous families with historical connections to Montgomery County. There are also comprehensive notes pertaining to the Price family genealogy in Virginia, Pennsylvania, and Indiana. Additionally, Price's diplomas from VPI are included.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by subject into the following series:
Series I: "Outlines of Montgomery County Families"
Series II: Compiled Genealogical Information
Series III: Subject files
Series IV: Diplomas
Index Terms
Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); Faculty; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.); University Archives; University History
Organizations:
Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute
Persons:
Price family
Contents List
- Series I: "Outlines of Montgomery County Families", 1940, n.d.
  - "Outlines of Montgomery County Families," Part I, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Typescript carbon copy with manuscript annotations. Contains information on the Barger, Broce, Cromer, Eskridge, Evans, Grissom, Harmon, Hawley, Henderson, Hornbarger, Keister, Kinzer, and Kipp families.
  - "Outlines of Montgomery County Families," Part II, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Typescript carbon copy with manuscript annotations. Contains information on Prices Fork, Price family.
  - "Outlines of Montgomery County Families," Part III, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Typescript carbon copy with manuscript annotations. Contains information on Long, Linkous, Lucas, Oliver, Parrish, Pate, Pepper, Plunkett, Ridpath, Shell, Slusher, Surface, Wall, and Walters families.
  - "Outlines of Montgomery County Families," Part IV, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Typescript carbon copy with manuscript annotations. Contains information on Allen, Altizer, Argarbrite, Barnett (Lyon), Bingham, Black, Bland, Brown, Burke, Calloway, Camper, Cook, Craig, Crockett, Croy, Crumpacker, Davis, Effinger, Evans, Hale, Hawkins, Haven, Hodge, Kanode, Kirby, Lybrook, Olinger, Pasco, Pepper, Perfater, Phlieger, Porterfield, Ribble, Robertson (Robinson), Shaffer, Sibold, Snidow (Snider), and Williams families.
- Series II: Compiled Genealogical Information, 1853, 1927-1949, n.d.
  - Price family genealogy notes - Pennsylvania, 1927-1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Price family genealogy notes - Indiana, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Price family genealogy (Folder 1 of 3), 1927-1943, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Price family genealogy (Folder 2 of 3), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Price family genealogy (Folder 3 of 3), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Biographical sketches of William Taylor Price and Margaret Ellen Price, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Barnett family genealogy, 1936-1939, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Black family genealogy, 1939-1940, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Broce family genealogy, 1944, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Brown family genealogy, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Buchanan family genealogy, 1931-1940, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Burk(e) family genealogy, 1940-1944, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Carter family genealogy, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Charlton family genealogy, 1937, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Conway family genealogy (includes a photocopy of the autobiography of William Buchanan Conway), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Craig family genealogy, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Crockett family genealogy (includes an 1853 letter written by Walter Crockett to Dr. Harvy Black, written from the Oregon Territory), 1853, 1935, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Cromer family genealogy, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Dade family genealogy, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Dalton family genealogy, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Eskridge family genealogy, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Evans family genealogy, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Fippen family genealogy, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Fitzhugh family genealogy, 1933-1935, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Peter Francisco family genealogy, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - French family genealogy, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Grissom family genealogy, 1938, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Harless family genealogy, 1942, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Harman family genealogy (1 letter), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Hoge family genealogy (2 p.), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Hornbarger family genealogy, 1927, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Howe family genealogy (2 p.), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Kanode family genealogy, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Keister (Keester) family genealogy, 1933-1938, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Copy of "Keister Family Genealogy" (ca. 100 p.), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Kinzer family genealogy, 1934, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Kipps (Kipp) family genealogy, 1949, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Kirby family genealogy, 1937-1946 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Ledbetter family genealogy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Linkous family genealogy, 1933-1938, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Long family genealogy, 1941-1943, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Lucas family genealogy (Folder 1 of 2), 1937-1941, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Lucas family genealogy (Folder 2 of 2), 1937-1941, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Lybrook family genealogy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - "The McClanahan's" by Rev. H. M. White (photocopy typescript), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - McCoy family genealogy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Miller family genealogy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Schaeffer family genealogy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Scott family genealogy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Shankin family genealogy (1 p.), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Shell family genealogy, 1933-1946, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Sibold (Siboldt) family genealogy, 1940, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Sifford family genealogy, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Slusher (Slusser) family genealogy, 1939, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Surface (Serface, Zirfals) family genealogy, 1931-1940, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Taylor family genealogy, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Thomas family genealogy, 1942, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Wall family genealogy, 1939-1943, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Walters family genealogy, 1942-1945, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Webb family genealogy, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Williams family genealogy, 1940-1945, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Wysor family genealogy, 1940, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 66)
- Series III: Subject files, 1933-1944, n.d.
  - Montgomery County files, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 67)
    Information includes photocopied newspaper articles and typescript articles and publications.
  - Southwest Virginia files, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Files relating to field trials for sporting dogs, 1933-1934, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Miscellaneous subject files (correspondence, articles, typescript publications), 1938-1944, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 70)
- Series IV: Diplomas, 1898, 1900
  - Harvey Lee Price, Bachelor of Science in Horticulture, VPI, 1898-06-15 (Folder 1)
  - Harvey Lee Price, Master of Science in Horticulture, Entomology, and Mycology, VPI, 1900-06-20 (Folder 1)